Guide to the Houston Area Community Services, Inc. records, 1986-2014 MS 670
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Houston Area Community Services, Inc. records
1986-2014
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Fuentes, Joe
MS 670
3.5 Linear Feet 4 boxes
The Houston Area Community Services records document the merged efforts of Bering Memorial United Methodist Church and Omega House to serve indigent and underserved patients of HIV/AIDS who could no longer be helped by the traditional medical community. The records are a comprehensive, but not all-inclusive, accounting for the functions of the administrative, financial, committee, business- and service-oriented areas for HACS primarily for the period 1998-2014 as overseen by President Ann Read.
Biographical / Historical
HACS was established in 1998 as a minority-based AIDS service to African American and Hispanic/Latino people living with HIV/AIDS. Objectives were to provide affordable, quality medical care, a pharmacy, behavioral health services and living assistance to individuals and families residing in Harris County and the surrounding areas. In 1997 the founder Joe Fuentes realized the need for an expanded health organization that would provide essential and specialty health services to patients living with chronic conditions such as HIV/AIDS. Mr. Fuentes was then able to extend the approach to all eligible residents of Harris County who were faced with the same social determinants that contributed to poor health.
In 1986 volunteers from Christ Church Cathedral and Bering Memorial United Methodist Church established Bering Community Service Foundation to provide compassionate care to people living with challenges posed by the new epidemic of HIV/AIDS. The same year, Eleanor Munger, founded a residential hospice, Omega House to provide a safe and caring environment for those living through the final stages of HIV/AIDS. Omega House joined with Bering to offer a holistic approach to care for those with HIV/AIDS and formed Bering Omega Community Services to offer a wide range of healthcare and social services for indigent, under-served clients in the greater Houston area.
In November 2016, Houston Area Community Services and Bering Omega merged as a Federally Qualified Health Center under the name Avenue 360 Health & Wellness.
Scope and Contents
The Houston Area Community Services records document the merged efforts of Bering Memorial United Methodist Church and Omega House to serve indigent and underserved patients of HIV/AIDS who could no longer be helped by the traditional medical community. The records are a comprehensive, but not all-inclusive, accounting for the functions of the administrative, financial, committee, business- and service-oriented areas for HACS primarily for the period 1998-2014 as overseen by President Ann Read.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open to the public.
Conditions Governing Access
Stored off-site at the Library Service Center. Please request this material via woodson@rice.edu or call 713-348-2586."
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The collection was donated by Avenue 360, formerly Houston Area Community Services, Inc., Joe Fuentes, Executive Director, on Oct. 26, 2016.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in four series, with subseries as appropriate: Series I Administrative/operational; Series II Committees; Series III Financial/budget/insurance; Series IV Organizations/business- and service-related
Index Terms
Subjects
Health care and medicine; Community-based social services; LGBTQ people
Document Types
documents
Places
Texas -- Houston
Subjects (Persons)
Fuentes, Joe
- Series I: Administrative / Operational
  - Articles of Incorporation, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Organizational chart (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Security (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Staffing
    - Training (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Timesheets/mileage (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Turnover (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Human Resources issues (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Website (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - IT project (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Project listing, 2008 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Gala "Sing for Hope", 2014 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Server usage report, 2007 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Incident reports (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Legal (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Vinson & Elkins (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Property
    - 2920 Fannin (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - 1407 Hawthorne (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Prospects/ideas (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - New facility sites (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Symposium: "Promising Practices in Community Health Center Design", 2013-02-06 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Property tax exemption, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Sales tax exemption (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Directory of services provided to Bering/Omega, 2008-04-28 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Volunteers (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Vision for future (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Quality management improvement plans (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Letters of collaboration (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Special events (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Safesite Storage (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Contracts/licenses (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Surveys (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - United Way Wage & Benefit Survey, 2006-07, 2008-09 (Box 1)
  - Marketing (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Development (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Grants manager (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Grant proposals (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Board of Directors
    - Meeting minutes & supporting materials (Box 1, Folder 36-37)
    - Retreat, 2008 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Retreat, 2010 (Box 1, Folder 38)
- Series II: Committees
  - Compliance Performance Improvement cmte. (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Comprehensive HIV Planning cmte. (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Executive cmte. (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Finance cmte. (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Planning cmte. (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Program cmte. (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Strategic Planning subcmte. (Box 2, Folder 7-8)
    - Strategic planning (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Strategic Plan, 2008 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Strategic Plan, 2012-2015 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Series III: Financial / Budget / Insurance
  - Total services revenue & cost (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - In-kind contribution (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Budgets & actual (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Accounts listing (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Accounts status (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Accounts status-Northern Trust (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Gift detail report, 2007-04-01-2007-04-30 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Capital expenditures (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Financial statement & audit, 2011-2012 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Summaries of benefit costs for staff (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - 401K plan participation (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Workers compensation (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Benefit Concepts, Inc. group insurance proposals
    - Renewal effective date June 1, 2008 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Renewal effective date June 1, 2009 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Renewal effective date June 1, 2010 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Renewal effective date June 1, 2012 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Renewal effective date June 1, 2013 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Renewal effective date Dec. 1, 2013 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Renewal effective date June 1, 2014 (Box 2, Folder 30)
- Series IV: Organizations / Business and Service related
  - Bering Memorial United Methodist Church (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - CACFP (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Care Center/Day Treatment, 2011 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Community health workers (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Community needs assessment, 2011-2012 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Consulting services (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Dental clinic (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Government affairs (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Greater Heights area Chamber of Commerce (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Harris County Appraisal District (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Harris County Healthcare Alliance (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Health & Human Services (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Health promotion (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - HIPAA privacy rule (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Hospice business plan proposal, 2011, 2013 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Housing assistance, 2011 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Houston Endowment annual report, 2011 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Houston Read Commission server maintenance, 2009 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - High Quality Management Program (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Strategies for Implementing Your HIV Quality Improvement Activities, 2009-04 (Box 3)
  - The Game Guide: Interactive Exercises for Trainers to Teach Quality Improvement in HIV Care, 2006-08 (Box 3)
  - A Guide to Consumer Involvement: Improving the Quality of Ambulatory HIV Programs, 2006-08 (Box 3)
  - Measuring Clinical Performance: A Guide for HIV Health Care Providers, April 2002; revised 2006 (Box 3)
  - HIVQUAL Group Learning Guide: Interactive Quality Improvement Exercises for HIV Health Care Providers, May 2002; revised 2006 (Box 3)
  - Making Sure Your HIV Care is the Best It Can Be, June 2002; revised August 2006 (Box 3)
  - HIVQUAL Workbook: Guide for Quality Improvement in HIV Care, 2006-09 (Box 3)
  - Solutions for HIV Clinics (Box 3)
  - Houston/Harris County Community Transformation Initiative Health Equity Policy Scan Report, 2012 (Box 3)
  - Demographic profile for registered clients, 2011 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Standards of care for HIV services (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - HIV diagnoses by zip code (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - HIV/AIDS needs assessment Houston area, 2014 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - HIV/AIDS data (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Montrose Counseling Center (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - National AIDS policy (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - One Voice Texas (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Ryan White Planning Council
    - 2009-2011 (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - 2012 (Box 3, Folder 29-30)
    - Grant log, 2009-2011 (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - Billing history, 2010 (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - Audit, 2011 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Licensing for home care (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Texas Association of Community Health Centers (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - The Resource Group (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Special care facilities (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Texas Workforce Solutions (Box 4)
  - Workforce solutions/Texas Workforce, 2009 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - "It's Far from Over;" Bering Omega Community Services (Box 4)